

# David Semedo

PhD · Auxiliar Researcher · Multimodal Deep Learning

Lisbon, Portugal

□ (+351) 917620446 | ☑ df.semedo@fct.unl.pt | 备 https://davidsemedo.com/ | ☎ Google Scholar |

## Summary.

PhD Assistant Researcher focused on Deep Learning approaches for Multimedia and Natural Language Processing.

His Ph.D. topic focused on computationally bridging vision and language over time, by modeling multimodal data interactions and their evolution, using deep learning architectures and large-scale data collections. Currently investigating open and domain-specific dialog systems, based on deep learning architectures, using data-driven approaches.

Expertise and Interests: Deep learning and machine learning for multimedia, natural language processing and data mining.

## Work Experience

#### Alexa Prize TWIZ Team Senior Researcher - Advisor and Mentoring

May 2021 - PRESENT

Amazon, USA

- ALEXA PRIZE 2021 TASKBOT CHALLENGE AMAZON
- TWIZ team website: https://twiz.ai/.

• Task-specific Multimodal Conversational Agents.

#### Senior Researcher - CMU Portugal iFetch Project

Sept. 2020 - PRESENT

NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Lisbon, Portugal

- Domain-specific multimodal dialog agents.
- · Neural approaches for multimodal dialog systems.

#### Research Assistant - GoLocal Project (CMUP-ERI/TIC/0046/2014)

Jan. 2019 - Aug. 2020

**NOVA School of Science and Technology** 

Lisbon, Portugal

- Temporal multimodal deep learning methods for cross-modal embedding learning and retrieval.
- Large-scale data mining and natural language processing for text understanding.

#### Research Assistant - COGNITUS H2020 project (Ref.687605)

Jan. 2016 - Dez. 2018

NOVA School of Science and Technology

Lisbon, Portugal

- Deep Learning and Machine Learning methods for multimodal (images/video and text) content semantic analysis and retrieval;
- Natural Language Processing for keyword extraction and understanding, SPAM filtering, and text search;
- Data mining from large-scale social-media collections;
- $\bullet \ \ {\it Collaboration with BBC R\&D, Queen Mary University, Vitec, FORTHNet, FORTH, ARRIS-Pace.}$

## Lab Instructor - LxMLS 2016

July 2016

Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa

Lisbon, Portugal

• Lab Instructor for Lisbon Machine Learning School 2016 (http://lxmls.it.pt/2016/).

#### Research Assistant - Restrict to Plan (QREN) Project (Ref.34091)

Jul. 2014 - Sep. 2015

NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Lisbon, Portugal

- Vehicle Scheduling Problems: Stochastic optimization strategies for large combinatorial problems;
- CPU Parallelization techniques for NUMA-based clusters;
- · Collaboration with TECMIC.

#### **Linux Distribution Developer and Maintainer**

Jan. 2013 - Jul 2013

Caixa Mágica Software

Lisbon, Portugal

- Debian Packages Full Cycle: creation, compilation, testing and deployment;
- Development of a Debian-based educational Linux distribution Openmillenium Project;
- · Responsible for the administration of Caixa Mágica distributions: package updates integration/compilation and deployment.

### **Junior Research Assistant**

Feb. 2013 - May 2013

NOVA SCHOOL OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Lisbon, Portugal

• Intrusion tolerant routing protocols for Ad-hoc Wireless Sensor Networks (IEEE 802.15.4). Advised by Prof. Henrique Domingues.

## **Education**

#### **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

Jan. 2016 - Jul. 2020

Ph.D., Computer Science

- Thesis: Bridging Vision and Language over Time with Neural Cross-modal Embeddings.
- · Advisor: João Magalhães.

#### **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

2013 - 2015 18 out of 20

M.Sc. Computer Science and Engineering

- Thesis: A Public Transport Bus Assignment Problem: Parallel Metaheuristics Assessment;
- · Advisors: Pedro Barahona and Pedro Medeiros.

#### **NOVA School of Science and Technology**

2010 - 2013

**B.Sc. Computer Science and Engineering** 

16 out of 20

## **Publications**

- Ferreira, R., M. Leite, D. Semedo, and J. Magalhães, **Open-Domain Conversational Search Assistant with Transformers**, European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR), 2021, Lucca, Italy **(CORE A)**
- Marcelino, G., D. Semedo, A. Mourão, S. Blasi, M. Mrak, and J. Magalhães, Assisting News Media Editors with Cohesive Visual Storylines,
   Proceedings of the 29th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2021, Chengdu, China (CORE A\*)
- Semedo, D., Towards Open-domain Vision and Language Understanding with Wikimedia, In Proceedings of the Web Conference, Wiki Workshop, 2021, Ljubljana, Slovenia
- Semedo, D., D. Carmo, R. Padnevych, and J. Magalhaes, **Contact-free Airport Borders with Biometrics-on-the-Move**, 9th IEEE International Workshop on Biometrics and Forensics, 2021, Rome, Italy
- Semedo, David and João Magalhães, Adaptive Temporal Triplet-Loss for Cross-Modal Embedding Learning, Proceedings of the 28th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2020, Seattle, WA, USA (CORE A\*)
- Marcelino, G., D. Semedo, A. Mourão, S. Blasi, M. Mrak, and J. Magalhães, A Benchmark of Visual Storytelling in Social Media, Proceedings
  of the 2019 ACM on International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR), 2019, Ottawa, Canada
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhães, **Dynamic-Keyword Extraction from Social Media**, European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR), 2019, Cologne, Germany (CORE A)
- Semedo, David and Joao Magalhaes, Cross-Modal Subspace Learning with Scheduled Adaptive Margin Constraints, Proceedings of the 27th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2019, Nice, France (CORE A\*)
- Semedo, David and Joao Magalhaes, **Diachronic Cross-Modal Embeddings**, Proceedings of the 27th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, 2019, Nice, France (**CORE A\***)
- Awad, George, Asad Butt, Keith Curtis, Yooyoung Lee, Jonathan Fiscus, Afzad Godil, David Joy, Andrew Delgado, Alan Smeaton, Yvette Graham, et al., TRECVID 2018: Benchmarking video activity detection, video captioning and matching, video storytelling linking and video search, Proceedings of TRECVID 2018, 2018
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhaes, Temporal Cross-Media Retrieval with Soft-Smoothing, Proceedings of the 26th ACM International Conference on Multimedia (ACM MM), 2018, Seoul, Republic of Korea (CORE A\*)
- Semedo, D., J. Magalhães, and F. Martins, Inferring User Gender from User Generated Visual Content on a Deep Semantic Space, 2018 26th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), 2018, Rome, Italy
- Semedo, D. and J. Magalhães, Convolutional Neural Networks for Medical Image classification NovaSearch at ImageCLEFmed 2016 Subfigure Classification Task, Working Notes of CLEF 2016 - Conference and Labs of the Evaluation forum, 2016, Évora, Portugal
- Semedo, D., P. Barahona, and P. Medeiros, Asynchronous Parallel Ant-Colony Optimization Strategies: Application to the Multi-Depot Vehicle Scheduling Problem with Line Exchanges, INForum-Simpósio de Informática (INFORUM). 2015, Covilhã, Portugal

## Scientific Projects Funding

#### Interactive Information Seeking Environments based on Deep State-aware Multimodal Embeddings

NOVA LINCS TARGETED RESEARCH ACTIVITIES PROJECT - BUDGET OF 11.7K€

April 2021 - Present

#### Alexa Prize 2021 Taskbot Challenge

Amazon, USA

SELECTED AS ONE OF 10 TEAMS - 250K\$ BUDGET + 500K\$ PRIZE FOR THE WINNING TEAM

May 2021 - Present

## ${\bf iFetch-MultiModal\,Conversational\,Agents\,for\,the\,online\,fashion\,marketplace,}\\ {\bf CMU-Portugal}$

CONTRIBUTED TO PROJECT PROPOSAL - BUDGET OF 1.5M€

2020 - Present

## Awards.

2019 **Student Travel Grant**, ACM Multimedia 2019. *Nice, France* 

## Activities\_

#### Organizer (Local Chair) and Bidder for the ACM Multimedia 2022

Lisbon, Portugal

PREMIER CONFERENCE ON MULTIMEDIA.

Oct. 2022

#### Volunteer at Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) conference

2020

#### **Industry Talk**

TITLE: BRIDGING VISION AND LANGUAGE OVER TIME: TEMPORAL CROSS-MODAL EMBEDDINGS, FARFETCH.

October 2020

#### **Webinar Talk**

TITLE: WEBINAR ON "DEEP MULTIMODAL AND CROSS-MODAL EMBEDDINGS", DATA SCIENCE PORTUGAL (DSPT).

July 2020

#### **ECIR 2020 Organization: Local Support**

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON INFORMATION RETRIEVAL 2020

April 2020

#### **Seminar Talk**

TITLE: BRIDGING VISION AND LANGUAGE OVER TIME WITH NEURAL CROSS-MODAL EMBEDDINGS, NOVA LINCS SEMINAR.

January 2020

#### Student Volunteer at ACM Multimedia 2019 conference

Nice, France

## Poster Presentation at 2nd NOVA Science day

NOVA SCIENCE DAY.

Lisbon

2019

2019

#### Poster Presentation at Encontro Ciência

Annual Science and Technology meeting for Portuguese researchers.

Lisbon

Organizer of TRECVID 2018 Linking Task: Social Media Video Storytelling

2016-2019

Gaithersburg, MD, USA

TRECVID IS THE PREMIER ANNUAL INTERNATIONAL WORKSHOP EVENT FOR EVALUATING CONTENT-BASED RETRIEVAL OF MULTIMEDIA AND DIGITAL VIDEO.

Nov. 2018

• Aimed to advance the area of visual summarization, with collaborative videos, images and texts from professional and social-media users.

#### **EXPO FCT**

SCIENCE FAIR SHOWCASING THE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOR HIGH-SCHOOL STUDENTS.

2012, 2016-2019

## **Program Committee and Reviewing Activities**.

2022	Program Committee Board (PCB), International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-ECAI 2022	2) Vienna, Austria
2021	PC Member - Reviewer, ACM Multimedia (ACM MM)	Chengdu, China
2021	PC Member - Reviewer, Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	Punta Cana, Dominican Republic
2021	Reviewer, Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-IJCNLP)	Bangkok, Thailand
2021	PC Member - Reviewer, International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)	Montreal, Canada
2021	<b>Journal Reviewer</b> , ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications and Applications (Q1)	
2020	PC Member - Reviewer, ACM Multimedia (ACM MM)	Seattle, USA
2020	<b>Journal Reviewer</b> , ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications and Applications (Q1)	
2019	PC Member - Reviewer, ACM Multimedia (ACM MM)	Nice, France
2018	Reviewer, ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR)	Michigan, USA
2018	Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)	Yokohama, Japan
2018	Reviewer, International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries (TPDL)	Porto, Portugal
2017	Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)	Bucharest,Romania
2017	Reviewer, IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo (ICME)	Hong Kong
2016	Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia Retrieval (ICMR)	New York, USA

_		
Tear	hing	
ICac	ııııg	

2021	Databases, B.Sc. Computer Science course
2020	Information Retrieval (Invited Lecture+Lab), Word Embeddings: Word2vec, skip-grams, Diachronic
2020	Embeddings, BERT, Applications. M.Sc. Computer Science course
2020	Computational Logic, B.Sc. Computer Science course
2019	Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering course
2018	Web Search and Data Mining, M.Sc. Computer Science course
2015	Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Computer Science course
2014	Algorithms and Data Structures, B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering course

## Students Advisoring\_

2021	<b>Ph.D. Rafael Ferreira</b> , (ongoing) Learning Reinforced Multimodal-Dialog Strategies for Conversational AI
	Agents, Co-advisor
2022	M.Sc. Carolina Lopes, (ongoing) Visual Question Answer for News Stories, Advisor
2022	<b>M.Sc. Cláudio Bartolomeu</b> , (ongoing) State-aware Embedding-based Interactive Search for News Images,
2022	Advisor
2021	M.Sc. Diogo Silva, (ongoing) Dialog Generation for Recommendation Agents, Co-advisor
2021	<b>M.Sc. Diogo Tavares</b> , (ongoing) Joint Dialog State Tracking and Slot Filling with the Transformer, Co-advisor
2021	<b>M.Sc. Jonas Rodrigues</b> , (ongoing) Metric Learning for Session-based Recommendation in Conversational
2021	Systems, Co-advisor
2020	<b>M.Sc. Rafael Ferreira</b> , Tracking Context in Conversational Search: From Utterances to Neural Embeddings,
2020	Co-advisor - 20 out of 20
2020	<b>M.Sc. Mariana Ferreira</b> , Knowledge-Driven Answer Generation for Conversational Search, Co-advisor - <b>19</b>
2020	out of 20
2020	<b>M.Sc. Ruslan Padnevych</b> , SmartyFlow - Robust Facial Biometrics for Virtual Identification, Co-advisor - <b>19</b>
2020	out of 20

## Computer Literacy \_\_\_\_\_

#### Languages

- Main Programming Languages (Proficient level): Python, C/C++, Java, SQL, Bash;
- **Programming Languages:** MATLAB, Javascript, OCaml, Prolog, Assembly.

#### **Deep Learning, Machine Learning and Data Science**

- **Deep Learning:** PyTorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Hugging Face, Theano;
- $\bullet \ \ \textbf{Machine Learning and Data Science:} \ \ \textbf{Python ML stack: Scipy+Pandas+Scikit-learn+Matplotlib}, Statsmodels, \textbf{XGBoost}, Scrapy; \\$
- Vision: OpenCV, Scikit-image, FFmpeg;
- NLP: NLTK Toolkit, Gensim, SpaCy, Tesseract (OCR), Stanford POS Tagger, Stanford NER, WordNet.

#### Big Data - Parallel/Distributed/Cloud Computing Libraries and Frameworks

- MPI, OpenMP, HTCondor, Hadoop, Spark, RMI;
- Cloud: Amazon AWS + S3.

#### **Other Frameworks and Technologies**

• LaTeX, RabbitMQ, Docker (Docker Compose), Elasticsearch, Android, GIT.

#### **Web Development**

- Frameworks: Django, Flask, Ruby on Rails;
- HTML/XHTML, XML, CSS, JQuery.

#### **Computing Infra-structures and Operating Systems**

- Multi-CPU and Multi-GPU deep learning machine setup and management;
- Proficient with Linux (Debian, CentOS) and Windows bash scripting/terminal.